בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is for us צ"ג. Tzadik
Gimmel. And we pick up at the very bottom of צ"ב עמוד
ב', Tzadik Bais amud Bais, where we're focusing on a debate between
רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, classic debate. Somebody buys an ox; the
standard would be assumed that somebody would be buying it for plowing.
It turns out that it was a goring ox. רב Rav says
it's a מקח טעות, mekach taus, and שמואל Shmuel says, no, you
can get your, no, the sale is valid, because even though the
majority buy it for plowing, there's a minority that buy it for
meat, and therefore there's no basis to claim מקח טעות. mekach taus.
So rather than framing this as a local debate in terms of
like מקח וממכר mekach umemkar and what types of assumptions have to
be made or explicit and not, the גמרא Gemara generalizes it as
a question about הולכין בממון אחר הרוב, holechin bemamon achar harov, whether
when you have a doubt about a monetary dispute and you're trying
to take money out of the possession of somebody that's מוחזק, muchzak,
that's in possession of it, and the normal principle is המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya, if you want to take money
out of my pocket, you have the burden of proof. What constitutes
a proof? Does majority constitute a proof? So framed that way, here
I am, I sold you the ox, you want your money back,
you have to prove that it was bought for the purpose of
plowing. According to רב, Rav, since that's the majority, that satisfies a
proof or a presumption or whatever that it was bought for that
purpose, and that's a basis of claiming מקח טעות. mekach taus. And
according to שמואל, Shmuel, the majority does not have that weight in
issues of monetary disputes when you're coming to take money out of
me. So even though the majority was that case, that does not
create the presumption or the proof that it was bought for that
purpose and you don't have a basis to claim מקח טעות. mekach
taus. So now the גמרא Gemara is sort of looking at that
in a wide range of cases where do we go by רוב
rov when it comes to monetary issues. So the גמרא Gemara picks
up at the bottom of צ"ב עמוד ב', Tzadik Bais amud Bais,
תא שמע, tasha, three lines from the bottom, תא שמע tasha with
the last word of the previous line: המוכר עבדו לחברו, hamocher avdo
lechavero, somebody sells a slave to his friend, ונמצא גנב או קוביוסטוס,
venimtza ganav o kubyustos, and he was found to be either a
burglar, the slave,
or a קוביוסטוס. kubyustos. So קוביוסטוס, kubyustos, רש"י Rashi and the רשב"ם
Rashbam following him basically saying it was a murderer or a,
but תוספות Tosafos says all the evidence is against that, and תוספות
Tosafos says other
other whatever sources make it sound that קוביוסטוס kubyustos is a dice
player, like משחק בקוביה, misachaik bekubya, right? So anyway he's a gambler,
all right? So these are things that are not good qualities in
a slave and would if they had been known would have constituted
a מקח טעות, mekach taus, a
מום. mum. הגיעו, higio, and the answer is tough luck, you know,
you know you get it you can't complain, all right? So it's
sort of like buyer beware. ליסטים או
מזויין או מוכתב למלכות, listis o mezuyan o muchtav lemalchus, however, if
he was an armed robber or if he was already a, you
know, an edict of execution had been passed on him, he was
going to be, he's going to be executed by the government. In
that case, that's something that's out of proportion to what you should
have expected, and אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך, omer lo harei shelcha
lefanecha, the buyer can say back to the seller, here, take back
what you sold me, give me my money back, this is not
what I bargained for. Okay, so it's interesting what exactly is the
difference between the first case and the second case. Is it that
the first case was within the range of tolerance of what you
might have been able to expect, the second one is outside of
that
range? Is it whether the phrase of הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha
lefanecha makes us think of how that phrase is used elsewhere in
cases of whether something is considered ניכר nikar or not ניכר? nikar?
If somebody has a death sentence passed on them, is it almost
like it's a type of a מום mum that is ניכר nikar
or not? But anyway, that's not our issue. What our issue is,
is how come in the first case the guy can't say, hey,
you know, this was not what I expected, give me my money
back, it's a מקח טעות? mekach taus? So the גמרא Gemara says
רישא, Reisha, מאי טעמא, mai tama, what's the reason in the first
case you're stuck with what you bought? לאו משום דרובא הכי איתנהו,
lav mishum derova hachi isnu, isn't it because the majority of
slaves are burglars or dice players? You know, this is of course
the, you know, just the reality of how when people own slaves,
the presumptions that they made about the character of their, you know,
of their slaves. So isn't it because that's the majority and therefore
you see you go by monetary matters אחר הרוב, achar harov, that
because that's the majority the person does not have a basis for
claiming מקח טעות? mekach taus? So doesn't that prove רב's Rav position
that you go by רוב? rov? So the גמרא Gemara says לא
כולהו הכי איתנהו, lo kulu hachi isnu, no, it's not the majority,
all slaves are like that! So as if it weren't bad enough
a minute ago that it was just assumed that most slaves were,
all slaves are that way, but normally you wouldn't go by רוב.
rov. Now I have to point out... out that this is, besides
the whole issues about attitudes towards slaves and the whole phenomenon of
slavery, whatever, but this is also just hard to fit into the
structure of what the גמרא's Gemara trying to prove. Right? The גמרא's
Gemara question is against חזקה Chazaka does רוב rov win out? Is
רוב rov strong enough against
חזקה? Chazaka? How's that relevant here? Here, I'm the seller, I already
have the money you paid me for your slave. I'm trying to
keep, you're trying to claim מקח טעות. Mekach Taos. So if רוב
rov wins and I could say, hey, you should have expected that
he might have had that problem, majority of slaves have that problem,
the רוב rov is reinforcing the חזקה. Chazaka. It's allowing me to
keep my money to prevent you from claiming מקח טעות. Mekach Taos.
So how is it relevant at all to the debate? And the
רשב"ם Rashbam tries to fit it in, but it's very hard to
understand how it's relevant. I'm just going to, I'm not going to
try to, kind of, solve that problem because there's no easy answer
to that. But anyway, at the end of the day, the גמרא
Gemara sort of dismisses that. But that doesn't fit our general pattern.
Our general pattern is to say, does רוב rov win out against
the חזקה? Chazaka? Here, רוב rov is coming to, like, reinforce a
חזקה. Chazaka. Let's keep on going. תא שמע, Tashma, שור שנגח את
הפרה. Shor Shenagach Es Hapar. This is a more straightforward case, and
also classic משנה. Mishnah. Okay, an ox gored a cow,
ונמצא עוברה בצדה, uvenimtza ubrah betzidah, and the fetus is lying by
the cow, it was a pregnant cow. And the question is ואינו
ידוע, veino yadua, it's not known, אם עד שלא נגחה ילדה, im
ad shelo nagcha yaldah, אם משנגחה ילדה. im mishenagcha yaldah. When did
the cow give birth to the fetus, or miscarry the fetus more
technically? Was it prior to the goring and therefore the dead fetus
is not the liability of the
owner
of the goring cow? Then it would mean that my goring cow
gored your cow that had, my goring ox I should say, let's
do ox and cow, make it easier.
My goring ox gored, שור שנגח את הפרה, Shor Shenagach Es Hapar,
my goring ox gored your cow that had already given birth. So
therefore it was worth less, right? A cow that had given birth
is worth less than a pregnant cow. So therefore I'm only liable
for a non-pregnant cow, that's משלא נגחה ילדה. mishelo nagcha yaldah. Or
do we say no, that it was still pregnant when my ox
had gored it and I'm liable for a pregnant cow, which is
a much, which is a greater liability? So we don't know when
it had miscarried, when it had, so what do we say? אם
עד שלא נגחה ילדה, im ad shelo nagcha yaldah, אם משנגחה ילדה?
im mishenagcha yaldah? So משלם חצי נזק, mshalem chatzi nezek, so אם
עד שלא נגחה im ad shelo nagcha before it was gored it
gave birth or only after it was gored it gave birth, meaning
that the goring caused it to miscarry and the goring killed the
fetus as well. So in that case משלם חצי נזק לפרה, mshalem
chatzi nezek lapar, I pay half damages for the value of a
cow that had given birth, because that my ox definitely gored, and
it's a, right, it's a שור תם, shor tam, my ox was
a first three times so it only pays half damages. Now the
question about the fetus, am I liable for that as well? So
we don't know, so ורביע לולד, verevia lavlad, you pay half of
the half. Right, if I were liable I'd pay half for the
fetus, if I wasn't I'd pay zero for the fetus, so it's
basically, this the גמרא Gemara in בבא קמא Bava Kamma says is
the position of סומכוס, Sumchus, ממון המוטל בספק חולקין, mamon hamutal besafek
cholkin, you split the difference, and therefore you pay half of the
half, you pay a quarter. Okay, but even with סומכוס, Sumchus, who
says ממון המוטל בספק חולקין, mamon hamutal besafek cholkin, that's only when
it's מוטל בספק. mutal besafek. But if you could go by רוב,
rov, why can't we use רוב rov to determine what happened? How
are we going to use רוב rov to determine what happened? Let's
take a look. By the way, I'm just going to mention parenthetically,
this is a question, does סומכוס Sumchus go by רוב rov or
not? Just because רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel were debating going by
רוב rov against the חזקה, Chazaka, right? סומכוס Sumchus who says ממון
המוטל בספק חולקין mamon hamutal besafek cholkin is normally understood to not
give as much weight to חזקה. Chazaka. Meaning normally we would say
I'm holding on to the money, you're trying to prove it, there's
a doubt, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav haraya. Comes along
סומכוס Sumchus and he sort of says no, if it's a doubt
you split it. So, one way of understanding סומכוס Sumchus is that
he doesn't give as much weight to חזקה. Chazaka. So it's not
necessarily clear right how you can bring in a סומכוס Sumchus position
to discuss this debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel whether רוב
rov wins out against חזקה, Chazaka, because סומכוס Sumchus operates from a
completely different type of a framework. His approach is always split the
difference. But we're going to sort of, again, just like bracket that,
we're going to assume that it's relevant. And now the question is,
so here you split it, but if you would go by רוב,
rov, why can't רוב rov sort of prove it? How would רוב
rov prove it? Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, והא ודאי, vha vada, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ואמאי, vamai, if you really do go by רוב, rov, לימא
הלך אחר רוב פרות. leima halach achar rov parot. Let's look at
most cows. ורוב פרות מתעברות ויולדות, verov parot mitabrot veyoldos, most cows
don't miscarry, most cows give birth to live birth. And this one
that miscarried, the explanation of the miscarriage is not that that was
a natural birth of the cow and it miscarried, the explanation would
be that it had been gored. Okay, והא vha and this cow
ודאי מחמת נגיחה הפילה, vadai machmat negicha hipila, it's because it had
been gored, or so if we go by רוב... rov... רוב, rov,
we can assume that the רוב rov would tell us that the
explanation of what happened was that the goring caused the miscarriage. And
therefore you should pay the full half amount for the ולד. vlad.
So if you don't, it shows that you don't go by רוב.
rov. Okay, even within like a סומכוס' Sumchus' position, you would not
go by רוב rov to determine the ספק. safek. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. No, התם משום דמספקא לן. hatam mishum d'mesapka
lan. No, no,
no, there I can say it's not a total רוב. rov. There's
a doubt that undercuts the רוב. rov. Why? דאיכא למימר מקמא אתא
ומביעותא הפילה. d'ika l'meimar mikama ata umibiyuta hepila.
It's true. In the majority of cases this would not have been
a normal birth, it would not have miscarried through a natural birth.
It was a result of the goring. But even within the context
of a result of the goring, there's two versions of what happened.
One is that the ox came straight at it, and it saw
the ox approaching it and charging at it, and from the fear
it miscarried. And in that case, even though the goring caused the
miscarriage, the owner of the ox isn't liable, because that's a גרמא.
grama. It wasn't the actual physical act of the goring itself, it
wasn't the contact that caused the miscarriage. So do we say מקמא
אתא, mikama ata, it came from in front of it? Where was
I?
מקמא אתא ומביעותא הפילה, mikama ata umibiyuta hepila, and it miscarried from
fear? ואיכא למימר, v'ika l'meimar, the alternative possibility is, מאחורא אתא, meachura
ata, it came from behind it, ומנגח נגחה, umengach nagcha, and it
gored it, והפילה, v'hepila, and the direct goring caused the miscarriage. So
therefore, even within the going by רוב rov and indicating that it
was a result of the goring, nevertheless, it's not clear that there's
still a ספק safek here about what happened in the context of
the goring.
וממונא המוטל בספק הוה, umamona hamutal besafek hava, וממונא המוטל בספק חולקין,
umamona hamutal besafek cholkin, and since it's a doubt you split it.
And the way תוספות Tosafot says it to even strengthen it a
little bit more is, you know, if you look at it sort
of like as a, you know, as a decision type of a
tree, right? You have רוב rov says that it was a, that
it was goring related,
goring related, and a מיעוט miut says that it was a natural
miscarriage, natural whatever miscarriage.
Okay, and within the רוב rov that it was goring related, you
have fear or you have direct goring. So even if we say
that the direct goring is a larger possibility than it miscarried off
by fear, but now you have two possibilities. Maybe it was a
natural miscarriage. And even within the likelihood that it was goring related,
there's also a possibility that it was fear. So those two combined
make it more or less treated as effectively, I mean, not exactly
be a 50/50, but it's enough of a balance ספק safek to
say חולקין cholkin for סומכוס. Sumchus. And therefore it's not a clear
and away רוב. rov. Okay, so this doesn't prove that you ignore
רוב. rov. Could be you go by רוב rov within the סומכוס
Sumchus and presumably with or without סומכוס, Sumchus, we don't feel סומכוס
Sumchus is relevant to this discussion, okay, but you see that you
would go by, could be you go by רוב rov and here
you don't really have רוב. rov. Okay, so we still haven't resolved
it. רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel debate, do you go by רוב
rov against חזקה? chazaka?
And now we're having, assuming it's going to be a similar debate
within סומכוס Sumchus that says ממונא המוטל בספק חולקין. mamona hamutal besafek
cholkin. We more look at the question of if there's a doubt
you split it rather than the חזקה chazaka issue, but even within
there we assume it would be the same debate. Do you go
by רוב rov or not by רוב rov to determine whether it's
considered to be a legitimate ספק? safek? And the גמרא Gemara says
you can't prove it from this case because this case might not
have been a רוב. rov. Yes.
So is it clear that the word caused by fear of being
gored, and then it turns out that she was actually gored? Yes.
That the fear is not, that the ox is not liable for
the fear?
If it was due to the fear of being gored, the ox
would not be liable, right. That's why you can use this as,
is that what you just said? Yeah, that's why you can use
this as part of the ספק safek that you're not liable, because
it's not directly the ox. What?
Even though it turns out that the fear was...
right, because it was gored, but if it first miscarried, you know,
if the fear caused the miscarriage, right, and even then it continued
goring it, the actual miscarriage itself would not be liable, correct. It's
not like, what's that rule about felony murder or something? It's not
like since it was in the perpetration of a goring, anything that
it caused was considered... no, no, the actual, you know what I'm
talking about? Like, anyway, so the actual, no, if the actual miscarriage
was the result of the fear, not the goring that came afterwards,
you would not be liable. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. לימא כתנאי. leima k'tanai. Let's say this debate of whether
you go by רוב rov or not parallels a debate of תנאים.
Tannaim. Anytime it says לימא כתנאי, leima k'tanai, you know the גמרא
Gemara is going to reject it, say it's not necessarily linked to
this debate of תנאים. Tannaim. כתנאי k'tanai means it's going to make
that assertion and keep with that. Okay, so לימא כתנאי. leima k'tanai.
Perhaps it goes like the following debate of תנאים. Tannaim. שור שהיה
רועה, shor shehaya ro'eh, an ox was grazing, ונמצא שור venimtza shor
ונמצא שור הרוג בצדו, Venimtza shor harug betzido, and right next to
it you saw a gored ox lying on the ground. אף על
פי שזה מנוגח וזה מועד ליגח, Af al pi shezeh menugach vezeh
muad ligach, this ox was gored and the grazing ox, it's just
docilely grazing nearby, not like it's got blood on its horns or
anything, you don't have a smoking gun, but nevertheless it has a
propensity to gore, you know that this is a
שור מועד. Shor Muad. Alright, so it's interesting if you translate this
into people, right? So somebody here who's a known thief, a burglar
is found in the vicinity of a house that was
burgled. Found in the vicinity, the person's a known burglar, does that
mean you can assume that this was the burglar? Here you go,
you have an ox that was known to be a מועד Muad
and next to it is a gored ox, אף על פי שזה
מנוגח וזה מועד ליגח. Af al pi shezeh menugach vezeh muad ligach.
זה מנושך, Ze menushach, it has been bitten, וזה מועד לישוך Vezeh
muad lishoch and this ox that's grazing nearby has a propensity to
bite, is a מועד, Muad, it's done it three times. אין אומרים
בידוע שזה נגח. Ein omrim beyadua shezeh nagach.
No, that's circumstantial. You can't say it must be this was the
ox that gored, בידוע שזה נגח וזה
נשך. beyadua shezeh nagach vezeh nashach. That's that you can't make that
assumption. ורבי אחא אומר, VeRabbi Acha omer, and רבי אחא Rabbi Acha
says, and the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains is that not only
can you make that assumption in that case where the ox already
was a מועד, Muad, but you can even make the assumption in
the following case, arguing with the תנא קמא. Tana Kama. גמל האוחר
בין הגמלים. Gamal ha'ocher bein hagamalim.
If a camel was אוחר. ocher. רשב"ם Rashbam gives two meanings of
the word אוחר, ocher, one is copulating and the other is sort
of
rutting? Is that a word? What does it mean when an animal
ruts? Isn't
that like its act of copulating or
something or no? Anyway, it's doing some type of a violent activity,
like it's being very active around it, what? משתגע. Mishtageia.
משתגע, Mishtageia, like going a little crazy or whatever, but he says
is משתגע mishtageia when it's in the act of
copulating, but even if you have a camel amongst other camels and
this camel here is acting a little bit wild,
either because it's copulating or for other reasons it seems like it's
in heat or something of that nature. It's in heat. It's in
heat. Right. Right. Exactly. Right. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says actively copulating
or it's in heat and it's acting violently, בין הגמלים ונמצא גמל
הרוג בצדו, bein hagamalim venimtza gamal harug betzido, and right nearby you
see a dead camel. Again you didn't see the actual act itself.
The camel normally doesn't have a propensity for violence, but you've seen
just recently it was being
very hyperactive and thrashing around, so he
says בידוע שזה הרגו, beyadua shezeh harago, yeah you can connect the
dots and you can assume that this killed it. Now this is
presumably by civil liability, it's also by ממון המזיק. mamon hamazik. It's
an interesting question would he say the same if you wanted to
make an accusation about a person, right? Not for that you probably
stole because
we know you go around and you have a violent nature and
then we saw somebody that was injured nearby you, would you say
the same? Or is he only saying it by ממון המזיק? mamon
hamazik? But anyway that's his claim. So what are they debating? Here
they're debating the question of can I prove that you owe me
money, that your camel gored my camel, your ox gored my ox.
The תנא קמא Tana Kama says you have to have real direct
evidence of it, you can't make circumstantial evidence and רבי אחא Rabbi
Acha says that you can use circumstantial evidence. Well that sounds pretty
much like the debate of הולכין בממון אחר הרוב. holchin bemamon achar
harov. Do you need absolute proof or can you make certain types
of assumptions? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. סברוה, Savruha, we assumed דרוב
וחזקה כי הדדי נינהו. derov vechazaka kihadadi ninhu. The question of going
by רוב rov was similar to the question of following a
חזקה. chazaka. Now חזקה chazaka means many things, like we said, חזקה
chazaka means the חזקת ממון, chezkat mamon, I'm in possession of the
money, but חזקה chazaka here means that it's established that you have
a propensity, it's something about your nature. So in this case about
let's start with the שור shor that was a מועד ליגח, muad
ligach, we know it has the propensity to gore. So we assumed
that whatever you say about using רוב rov as a basis for
winning a ממון mamon case, you would say the same about חזקה.
chazaka.
So לימא רב דאמר כרבי אחא, leima Rav de'amar k'Rabbi Acha, רב
Rav who says you go by רוב rov would say like רבי
אחא Rabbi Acha that would say that you would go by sort
of an ox that had a propensity to gore you could assume
it was the goring and an ox that was being violent and
in heat you could assume or camel you could assume that was
the one that was to blame. ושמואל veShmuel and שמואל Shmuel says
no there's no direct evidence, האי דאמר כתנא קמא hai de'amar keTana
Kama he says like the תנא קמא Tana Kama you need direct
evidence and that's what the תנא קמא Tana Kama says, so it
seems like it's exactly that debate, do you need direct evidence or
can you prove it more through circumstance or רוב rov etc. So
אמר לך רב, amar lach Rav, so now here the גמרא Gemara
is very interesting and makes a distinction between these two concepts. אמר
לך רב, amar lach Rav, רב Rav would say to you אנא
דאמרי אפילו לתנא קמא. ana de'amri afilu leTana Kama. No, when I
say you go by רוב rov in this case I could agree
to the תנא קמא Tana Kama that you would not assume blame
it on the ox that had a propensity to gore even though
there was another ox nearby, why? עד כאן
לא קאמר תנא קמא התם, Ad kan lo ka'amar Tanna Kamma hasam,
when did the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma say there you don't blame
it on the gore on the ox that has a propensity to
gore? אלא דלא אזלינן בתר חזקה, Ela d'lo azlinan batar chazakah, you
don't go by a חזקה, chazakah, by a propensity, אבל בתר רובא
אזלינן, aval batar ruba azlinan, you go by a רוב. rov. Now,
what's exactly the difference? So the difference is
is that well you know let's finish and read the next statement
of שמואל Shmuel and then that'll clarify it in both ways. ושמואל
אמר לך, Ve'Shmuel amar lach, שמואל Shmuel will say to you, "אנא
דאמרי אפילו רבי אחא." Ana de'amri afilu Rabbi Acha. I would say
even though I don't go by רוב, rov, here I could agree
to רבי אחא. Rabbi Acha. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי אחא התם
אלא דאזלינן בתר חזקה. Ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Acha hasam ela
d'azlinan batar chazakah. רבי אחא Rabbi Acha
who says you blame it on the ox that has a propensity
to gore, you blame it on the camel, that's because we follow
the חזקה chazakah of this animal, דהוא גופא מחזיק, d'hu gufa machazik,
and this is a helpful three words. That is something you know
about this particular animal. This particular animal, this ox, you know it
has a propensity to gore. So therefore we're willing to say that
it acted based on its nature. We don't know who gored, we
know this has its nature, we know it was right nearby, we
know the camel was engaged in violent activity, so therefore because we
know it specifically about this animal, even though we don't know 100%
he did it, it is circumstantial, but that's a good enough basis
to say it acted according to its nature. Okay, אבל בתר רובא
לא אזלינן, aval batar ruba lo azlinan, but a
general רוב rov we wouldn't go. What would be a general רוב?
rov? Let's contrast it to the other cases we had, right? You
bought an ox, a cow from me, and you said that you
were buying and your claiming, "Oh well, of course I was buying
it
for purposes of plowing, that's what almost everybody does," and I'm saying
that doesn't prove it. How am I supposed to know who you
are, right? So I don't know anything about you in particular. I
don't have to assume that you are from the majority of people
that buy it for plowing. I don't go by רוב, rov, okay?
But if I know something specifically about the person in front of
me then I can make certain assumptions. All right, so let's take
the other case. The ox gored the cow and you don't know
when it gave birth. All right, so that's also you don't know
anything about this ox and this cow that would lead you to
say it gave birth sooner or later. You just want to go
by a general statistics about when do cows give birth, natural birth
versus miscarriage, right remember that case? So you want to use like
a general
statistic, שמואל Shmuel says that doesn't mean anything you know because there's
always going to be the people that fall in the minority percentage
of the statistic. Yeah, so the majority is this way, who's to
tell you this person isn't from the minority? But if you know
something specific about this person or this ox, then we can make
an assumption maybe that would be enough at least for ממונית mammonis
purposes to assume that people acted based on what we know about
them in general. So שמואל's Shmuel position saying חזקה chazakah is weightier
than רוב, rov, okay, actually makes a certain amount of sense, okay?
How do you explain, are people with me here, right about what
the logic is, how do you explain the opposite position? Because actually
the גמרא Gemara in the beginning of חולין Chullin had a question:
רובא וחזקה, רובא עדיף או חזקה עדיף? ruba v'chazakah, ruba adif or
chazakah adif? Okay, and the גמרא, Gemara, and now again that חזקה
chazakah is slightly different, that's a status quo חזקה chazakah as opposed
to a propensity חזקה, chazakah, we just have to have the same
word mean five different things to keep you guessing, but anyway, but
the גמרא's Gemara conclusion there is רובא עדיף, ruba adif, the רוב
rov is better. Because you could also understand the majority, the רוב
rov argument is just because this ox has a propensity to gore,
right, you know, does that mean that דווקא davka today it gored
this thing? Right like I said like okay fine I'm a burglar
and you found me near a house that was burgled, right, so
does that mean that just because that's my nature that's what I
did right now? But if you actually have a רוב, rov, the
רוב rov is telling
you that in this particular we don't know anything about you in
particular but we could say it's a good bet it's a 90%
likelihood that you were buying the ox for plowing. It's a 90%
likelihood that the ox miscarried as a result of the goring. We
don't know anything about the ox, we don't know anything about the
cow, we don't know anything about whatever, but we know with a
high degree of confidence that just based on statistics, probability, this is
most likely what we were talking about. So it's like very interesting,
one is where you know something concretely about you but that doesn't
tell us what the likelihood is that it happened in this case,
okay? The other is something we don't know anything about you, we
know something about the general population, but that means that the majority
like the the majority of the time this will be a right
assumption. So it's very interesting to think about how those operate differently
and the גמרא Gemara suggests that you could go either way. So
it says רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel are debating by רוב, rov,
it's possible רב Rav would go by רוב rov and not by
חזקה, chazakah, it's possible שמואל Shmuel would go by חזקה chazakah and
not by רוב. rov. People good with that? Okay, so I think
that that was probably the most conceptual point of like this to
this issue about thinking the difference between רוב rov and חזקה. chazakah.
All right so now the גמרא Gemara continues. תא שמע, Ta shema,
come and hear. So now we said it's not that debate of
תנאים Tannaim but now we're going to make it a different debate
of תנאים. Tannaim. תא שמע. Ta shema. המוכר פירות לחברו לזרען ולא
צמחו. Hamocher peiros l'chavero l'zoran v'lo tzamchu. Now we Okay, here's our
משנה. Mishna. You sell fruit and which includes like seeds or whatever,
let's say wheat, you know, grain, and you planted them and they
did not, they did not grow. Okay, so ואפילו זרע פשתן, v'afillu
zera pishtan, even if you bought flaxseed, where the majority of people
buy flaxseed for the purpose of planting, so there was a presumption
that the guy was buying it for the purpose of planting.
He can't claim, אינו חייב באחריותן, eino chayav b'acharayutan, the seller has
no liability because I can, you know, you can't claim it was
clear I was buying it for planting, מקח טעות, mekach taus, etc.
No, you don't go by רוב. rov. That sounds very much like
שמואל. Shmuel. That sounds almost exactly like the ox that turned out
to be a goring ox. So מאי לאו, mai lav, מאי, mai,
אפילו אפילו. afillu afillu. What does the word 'even' if you sell
flaxseed? לאו, lav, isn't the point exactly of highlighting the flaxseed to
tell me, אפילו זרע פשתן דרובא לזרעא זבני, afillu zera pishtan d'ruba
l'zara zavni, even flaxseed where most people or the majority of flaxseed
is bought for the purpose of planting, אפילו הכי לא אזלינן בתר
רובא. afillu hachi lo azlinan basar ruba. The whole point in the
משנה mishna is to tell, say, even though it's clear that flaxseed
a majority of the time is bought for this purpose, I'm sorry,
no מקח טעות. mekach taus. You don't go by רוב. rov. That's
not a basis of claiming מקח טעות. mekach taus. And that's almost
like an exact שמואל Shmuel פסק. psak. So you have a משנה
mishna going like שמואל. Shmuel. תנאי היא. tannai hi.
Yes, you're right. The author of our משנה mishna is like שמואל,
Shmuel, but רב Rav has other תנאים tannaim in a ברייתא. braisa.
דתניא, d'tanya, exactly a ברייתא braisa paralleling this משנה. mishna. המוכר פירות
לחברו לזרען ולא צמחו. Hamocher Peiros l'chavero l'zra'an v'lo tzamchu. So זרעוני
גינה שאין נאכלין. zir'onei gina she'ein ne'echalin. Now this in our משנה
mishna was the position of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel. Okay, in the ברייתא braisa this is the תנא קמא. tanna
kamma. If they are, you know, the, like, vegetable seeds that nobody
eats, so it's not just a רוב, rov, they're only bought for
the purpose of planting, חייב באחריותן, chayav b'acharayutan, you're liable. זרע פשתן,
zera pishtan, flaxseed, where it's the majority is for that purpose but
not the totality, אינו חייב באחריותן, eino chayav b'acharayutan, you're not liable.
So that's our תנא קמא. tanna kamma. אין הולכין בממון אחר הרוב.
ein holchin b'mamon achar harov. Majority doesn't make it a מקח טעות.
mekach taus. But now we have dissenting views. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi
Yossi omer, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says, נותן לו דמי זרע. nosein
lo d'mei zera. No, I'm sorry, if it's at least by the
flaxseed case, you have to reimburse him for the flaxseed. So here
you go. The debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel is the
debate of the תנא קמא tanna kamma and רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says you have to reimburse him. You needed
to have assumed that he was buying it for the purpose of
planting. אמרו לו, amru lo, so then somebody else said to him,
אמרו לו, amru lo, there's a גמרא gemara that they said back
to him, where were we? הרבה לוקחין אותו לדבר אחר. harbe lokchin
oso l'davar acher. No, even flaxseed you can't assume that flaxseed was
for the purpose of planting. There's many other reasons people buy flaxseed.
So it sounds like the whole debate of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
and the אמרו לו amru lo is what is the, what are
the numbers, right? Is it true that there's a large that the
significant majority buy it for planting or not? אמרו לו amru lo
debates that question and we'll get into that in a minute. But
it seems that they both agree that if it really were true
that a significant majority were only buying it for the purpose of
planting, it would be a basis of מקח טעות mekach taus and
you would go by רוב. rov. So it really seems that this
is the debate. The תנא קמא tanna kamma is not concerned at
all with the flaxseed, I don't care about רוב, rov, and רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi and the אמרו לו amru lo are concerned with
it and say that that is a basis for מקח טעות. mekach
taus.
So that's what the
גמרא gemara says.
Yeah, לשמואל? l'Shmuel? That's, at least רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, fine, that's
what, at least רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. So the גמרא gemara says
מאן תנאי, man tannai, so how do the תנאים tannaim line up?
אילימא רבי יוסי ואמרו לו, eileima Rabbi Yossi v'amru lo, maybe רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi and אמרו לו, amru lo, maybe the אמרו לו
amru lo of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is saying you don't go
by רוב. rov. So the גמרא gemara says that's not true, that's
just what I just said. תרווייהו בתר רובא אזלי. tarvayeihu basar ruba
azli. The אמרו לו amru lo also assumes you go by רוב.
rov. He's just saying that you don't have the רוב rov to
back you up here.
Now the גמרא gemara now frames it in a different way, not
just that it's critiquing the רוב, rov, but actually positioning a different
רוב. rov. מר אזיל בתר רובא דאינשי, mar azil basar ruba d'inshei,
one goes by the majority of people, ומר אזיל בתר רובא דזריעה,
umar azil basar ruba d'zri'ah, and the other goes by the majority
of the seed. So the way the גמרא gemara reads it, which
is I think a funny read, but when it says הרבה לוקחין,
harbe lokchin, הרבה harbe means like many, many doesn't mean the majority,
it just means that there are many other reasons why people do
it. But the גמרא gemara means הרבה harbe as רוב. rov. The
גמרא gemara actually reads the אמרו לו amru lo as saying the
majority of people buy it for other purposes. So what's the debate?
So what is the choice? Do the majority buy it for planting
or for other purposes? So the גמרא gemara now frames the debate
as the following. Majority of flaxseed is sold for planting. If you're
a farmer, you're buying a hundred pounds of flaxseed. But the majority
of people, right, the other ten out of every ten people, one
is a farmer who buys a hundred pounds and ten are other
people who buy a pound each. And they're buying a pound each
to mix it into their what do you use flaxseed for, those
like smoothies or whatever? To mix it in. to their health smoothies,
okay? So the majority, nine out of ten people, buy it for
eating,
but the majority of flaxseed is sold for planting. Now of course
if that really were true, then you should use that as a
fact to determine what the purpose of the buying it for, what
quantity or whatever. Anyway, that's the way the גמרא Gemara is framing
it. But the גמרא, Gemara, rather than saying
exactly.
So anyway, but rather than saying that the אמרו לו Amru Lo
is not saying there's a different רוב, rov, just saying like, I
don't think there's such a רוב rov here, that's the way I
think we would read it. The גמרא Gemara is saying they're both
saying you go by רוב, rov, but they're debating how do you
assess the רוב? rov? By the majority of the object that's sold
or the majority of the people. Now,
but neither way, both are saying you would use רוב rov as
a basis for מקח טעות. mekach taut. So now the debate is
between the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that is completely unconcerned with the
flaxseed and doesn't care about רוב, rov, only cares about like vegetable
seeds when it's one hundred percent, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and
the אמרו לו Amru Lo who say if there's a רוב, rov,
that's a basis for מקח טעות. mekach taut. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, אלא אי תנא קמא ורבי יוסי, ella ee Tanna
Kamma ve-Rabbi Yose, so the debate is either תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
who doesn't care about רוב rov and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose who
does, who would go by רוב rov of the seed itself, of
the quantity of the seed. אי תנא קמא והאמרו לו, ee Tanna
Kamma ve-Amru Lo, or again תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and the אמרו
לו, Amru Lo, אמרו לו, Amru Lo, תנא קמא Tanna Kamma doesn't
care about רוב rov and the אמרו לו Amru Lo does except
he goes by the רוב rov of the buyers. So at the
end of the day, we're saying that our משנה Mishnah that doesn't
care about flaxseed and says it's not a מקח טעות mekach taut
is שמואל. Shmuel. But there is a ברייתא braita position of רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose and an אמרו לו Amru Lo who do care
about רוב rov and say it is a basis for מקח טעות.
mekach taut. So at the end of the day, the debate of
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel is the debate of the תנאים. Tannaim.
And in terms of the general question of הולכין בממון אחר הרוב,
holchin be-mammon achar ha-rov, not in a מקח טעות mekach taut מכר
וממכר mecher u-mimkar context, but in general, the גמרא Gemara did not
resolve it. We had an interesting parallel debate about the goring ox
with a propensity about do you go by
חזקה chazakah by ממון, mammon, but we really haven't, that was the
debate of those תנאים, Tannaim, but we really haven't resolved the general
question of הולכין בממון אחר הרוב. holchin be-mammon achar ha-rov. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara continues. תנו רבנן מה הוא נותן לו Tanu rabanan:
Mah hu noten lo? In a case where it was a מקח
טעות, mekach taut, let's say it was, you know, the vegetable seed,
everybody could agree it was מקח טעות, mekach taut, everybody buys it
for planting and you sold me seeds that were not fertile, that
you know, so what do you have to reimburse me for? דמי
זרע ולא הוצאה. Demei zera ve-lo hotza'ah. So the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma says like what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose said earlier, when there
is going to be a reimbursement, it's going to be for, you
know, the cost of the seed, okay, not for any expenses. ויש
אומרים אף הוצאה. Ve-yesh omrim: af hotza'ah. And some say no, even
for the expenses. Now of course that's like גרמא grama and גרמא
בנזיקין, grama bi-nezikin, you know, why should I be liable for that?
So okay, so the רשב"ם Rashbam says it seems to him it's
a קנס knas or from people who remembers בבא קמא Bava Kamma
it's like a דין דיני דגרמי, din dinei de-garmi, okay? It's clearly,
you know, it's like yes it is causation but a type of
causation that according to this position we wanted to make you liable
for. It's like, you know, when the computers they sell you these,
you know, backup tapes or whatever and what they say well,
you know, if the backup ever like you lose any data, we'll
reimburse you for the cost of the backup tape. It's like, I
don't care about the cost of the backup tape. I care about
all the data that I lost, right? So it's like the seed
might be a minor part of the actual cost that came to
this person because he bought this faulty seed. So therefore it says
that you are going to be חייב. chayav. Of course that really
means that people, I'm not kidding here, people that sell these types
of things would probably have to get serious insurance, you know, liability
insurance. I mean imagine that, right? I mean it's not so פשוט
pashut of the poor farmer, it is true the poor farmer, but
how about the poor seed
seller?
Right and exactly.
So is
it so does do you have to prove negligence on my part,
like that I genuinely believed it to be that, right, you might
have to prove negligence if I have to now reimburse you for
all those expenses. And the other thing that the גמרא Gemara that
תוספות Tosafot already addressed is how do we know it was my
fault and not your fault? How do we know you planted it
the right way, you watered it the right way, you treated it
the right way? Okay, so it could be that there are a
lot of hurdles you would have to get over in order for
me to reimburse you for your expenses, okay? But at least that
would be sometimes under some circumstances where I was negligent and it
could be proven that you could get reimbursement even for your expenses
according to this opinion. Okay, ויש אומרים אף הוצאה. ve-yesh omrim af
hotza'ah. מאן ויש אומרים Man yesh omrim? Who's the ויש אומרים? yesh
omrim? אמר רב חסדא רבי שמעון בן גמליאל היא. Amar Rav Chisda:
Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel hi. It's our רבי שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabbi
Shimon ben Gamliel. So hi רבי שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabbi Shimon ben
Gamliel, which רבי שמעון בן גמליאל Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel are you
associating this with? Where did you get that name from? So maybe
in our משנה, Mishnah, אימא רבי שמעון בן גמליאל דמתניתין? ee-ma Rabbi
Shimon ben Gamliel de-matnitin? How about our משנה? Mishnah? דתנן המוכר פירות
לחבירו וזרעם ולא צמחו ואפילו זרע פשתן אינו חייב באחריותם. detnan ha-mocher
perot la-chavero ve-zaram ve-lo tzamchu va-afilo zera pishtan eino chayav be-achrayutam. So
our משנה Mishnah says even flaxseed you're not liable again because maybe
you weren't buying it for planting. So then we'll read it with
the parentheses, חוץ מזרוני גינה שאינם נאכלים חייב באחריותם. chitz mi-zironi ginah
she-einam ne'echalin chayav be-achrayutam. The fact that the משנה Mishnah only excludes
flaxseed, I mean includes flaxseed, means that if it was something like
the implicit position already of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is that
if it was something like vegetable seed... that were only for planting,
you would be liable. That's already implicit in the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma that if it's something that's only for planting you would be
liable. So אימא סיפא, eima seifa, so then what is רבן שמעון
גמליאל Rabban Shimon Gamliel adding? רבן שמעון גמליאל אומר זרעוני גינה שאינן
נאכלין חייב באחריותן, Rabban Shimon Gamliel omer zironei gina she'einan ne'echalin chayava
achrayusan, that you are that if it's vegetable seeds you're liable because
that's their only for planting. So that was already implicit in the
תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. תנא קמא נמי הכי קאמר. Tanna Kamma nami
hachi ka'amar. That's also implicit in the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. זרע
פישתן הוא דאינו חייב באחריותן, zera pishtan hu de'eino chayav beachrayusan, flaxseed
are not חייב chayav because I could say you bought it for
other purposes. הא זרעוני גינה שאינן נאכלין חייב באחריותן, ha zironei gina
she'einan ne'echalin chayava beachrayusan, implicit is you would be liable. So what's
רבן שמעון גמליאל Rabban Shimon Gamliel adding that's not implicit in the
תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? אלא לאו, ella lav, so the Gemara says
if they're seen to say the same thing, it's a classic move
of the Gemara.
We're going to assume that there's some other debate going on here.
אלא לאו הוצאה איכא בינייהו. ella lav hotza'ah ika beiniyhu. What they're
debating is the degree of liability. Are you liable just for the
seed, or are you liable even for the expenses of the farmer?
מר סבר דמי זרע, mar savar dmei zera, that you're only liable
for the seed, ומר סבר אף הוצאה. u'mar savar af hotza'ah. And
then רבן שמעון גמליאל Rabban Shimon Gamliel would say no,
you're fully liable, even for the expenses. So maybe let's read that
in and say that that's a רבן שמעון גמליאל Rabban Shimon Gamliel
position. So the Gemara says one minute, ממאי, mi-mai, how what's where
do you get off you know what's your basis of saying that?
דילמא איפכא, dilma ipcha, first of all, maybe even if they are
debating the degree of liability, how you know רבן שמעון גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel is the one who has the heavier liability? Maybe
it's the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. Gemara says no, הא לא קשיא,
ha lo kashya, that if that was your only criticism, then that
would not be sufficient. כל תנא בתר לטפויי מילתא קאתא. kol tana
basar le-tefu-ei milta ka-atei. We generally assume that the second opinion is
coming to go even further than the first one. If the first
one already said you're liable, or implicitly said you're liable, and the
second one says yeah you're liable, makes it more explicit, so presumably
they're coming to say even higher liability. So yes, I do want
to say that רבן שמעון גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is saying
that you're more liable, even for the expenses. So the Gemara says
fine, ודילמא כולה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל היא, ve-dilma kulei Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel hi, nevertheless, you can't really prove there's a debate going
on here. Maybe רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is
just clarifying the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and it's all really the
position of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. וחסורי מחסרא
והכי קתני. ve-chasorei mechasra ve-hachi katani. Some don't have the word וחסורי
מחסרא, ve-chasorei mechasra, they're saying we're not even claiming there're missing words,
we're just saying רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel like
you know לפירושי מילתא דתנא קמא
קאתא. le-firushei milta de-Tanna Kamma ka-atei. He's just coming to make explicit
what was already implicit. He's not coming to give a different position.
Okay? And here's what we really mean to say. המוכר פירות לחבירו
וזרען ולא צמחו ואפילו זרע פישתן אינו חייב
באחריותן. hamocher peirot le-chavero ve-zar'an velo tzamchu ve-afillu zera pishtan eino chayav
beachrayusan. Even פישתן pishtan you're not חייב, chayav, דברי רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל. divrei Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Now we'll take out the parentheses.
That's what רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל אומר זרע פישתן הוא דאינו חייב באחריותן הא זרעוני
גינה שאינן נאכלין חייב
באחריותן. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer zera pishtan hu de'eino chayav beachrayusan
ha zironei gina she'einan ne'echalin chayava beachrayusan.
Yeah, who says there're two opinions here? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel is just clarifying. Fine, פישתן pishtan you're not חייב,
chayav, גינה gina you are. It doesn't mean that they're really debating.
So there's no you can't make a claim that רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel because he's being more explicit says that
you're liable for expenses. אלא ella fine, says the Gemara, הא רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. ha Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Here's the רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that's clear that you're liable for
that will be the basis for me to say you're liable for
expenses.
אלא הא רבן שמעון בן גמליאל דתניא, ella ha Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel de-tanya, we learned in a ברייתא: Baraita: המוליך חטים לטחון, hamolich
chitin lit-chon, you go ahead and you bring your wheat to the
to the guy who owns the mill, and you want him to
grind your wheat. ולא לתתן, velo latatun, and what he did is
he did not I don't know what the English word for this
is but you basically put them in water and you remove their
husk. He didn't dehusk them. Okay? And therefore he ground them with
the husk, so he made bran, rather than making fine flour.
ועשו סובין או מורסן, ve-asu subin o murtan, and he made them
basically, I don't know, one of these is bran and I'm not
sure what the other is, but either of them they're not refined
flour. What does it say?
Sounds like whole wheat.
Whole wheat? A bran is like just the just the bran? Okay.
So anyway so anyway he made it non-fine flour, bran or whole
wheat, okay, which obviously was clearly a lesser quality, right, until now
the hazards of health concerns that always was like what the poor
people ate because that was more quantity and it didn't taste as
good. All right, so you made he made it lesser, you know,
he hurt the quality of the wheat because he didn't process it
in the right way.
Did he say bran or coarse bran?
Bran or coarse bran, excellent. Okay. קמח לנחתום, kemach lenachtom, you brought
your flour to a baker, ואפאו פת פולין, ve'afa'o pat pulin, and
he made it into bread which is falling apart, okay, או בהמה
לטבח, o behemah letabach, or your animal to the butcher, וניבלה, venivla,
and he shechted it incorrectly and turned it into a נבילה. neveilah.
So basically you brought all these things to these tradespeople and they
damaged effectively the raw material you gave them, okay? They didn't only
not improve it, but they actually now, you know, you're worse off
than before. So חייב, chayav, they are liable to you. This is,
you know, מפני שהוא כנושא שכר, mipnei shehu k'nosei sachar,
because it's like they are a being paid. Now what does it
mean it's like they are being paid? So the גמרא Gemara actually
where this comes up in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia whatever says that
they are being paid, okay, which raises an interesting question, like if
I had somebody a friend say oh no problem I'll שחט shecht
your בהמה behemah for free why do you have to go whatever
and I'm not paying them they actually don't have liability because if
they're not paid they don't know it's sort of like the whole
principle of like I mean they're not שומרים shomrim as much as
they're אומנים, umnim, they're craftspeople, okay I'll talk in a minute about
that question about where their liability comes from, okay but anyway the
bottom point is that if they're being paid then they're liable this
is considered to be negligence or close to negligence, maybe not negligence
because negligence even if they were doing it for free they'd be
liable, but it's actually but it's not like a total accident, it's
something they could have been more careful about, so it's a so
in those cases right people remember now here I said I wasn't
going to talk about it but I'll just say very quickly I
don't know if people remember this right that a
שומר חינם shomer chinam is liable in פשיעה, peshiya, a שומר שכר
shomer sachar is liable in גניבה ואבידה gneivah v'aveidah
and a שואל shoel is חייב chayav in אונס. ones. So presumably
it's saying that the level of liability for these things happening although
I don't know you would think that I mean I assume sometimes
accidents happen when I'm שחט shechting something but you would think that
to forget to do one of the processes of removing the brain
is real negligence you know for for a tradesperson. But the גמרא
Gemara seems to say that the level of like it's not gross
negligence it's some small degree of fault on the other hand it's
not a complete accident so because you're being paid your liability is
equal to that of a שומר shomer who's being paid which is
you're liable for anything that's not a complete accident. If you weren't
being paid you'd be exempt because if you weren't being paid we
would sort of see it as parallel to a שומר shomer who's
not being paid who's only liable for gross negligence. Okay so that's
the basic point here therefore the these tradespeople are liable but then
it says fine that's not relevant to us yet. Here's רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer נושא לו דמי בושתו ודמי בושת אורחיו. notsei
lo dmei boshto v'dmei boshet orchav. Very nice you're saying oh I'm
sorry here I'll reimburse you for your wheat or for your bread
or for your meat it's like I've got my kid's wedding tonight
and this was supposed to be the meat that we were serving.
Doesn't help me that you're just paying me for my meat. What
about that embarrassment about all of my guests? What about you've ruined
my entire event? Okay so רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel says fine you're going to have to pay for that. You're
going to have to pay for the impact that that had on
me and on all of my guests and so on. Okay that's
a real like you know that's a real that's like a real
type of a גרמא בנזיקין grama b'nizikin but you know again a
type of maybe a גרמי garmi or something of that nature. וכן
היה רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר V'chein haya Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer מנהג גדול היה בירושלים. minhag gadol haya b'Yerushalayim. There was a
great custom or practice in Jerusalem, המוסר סעודה לחברו וקלקלה, hamoseir seudah
l'chavero v'kilkela, you call up a caterer and you pay the guy
ten thousand dollars to go ahead and to cater the event and
they make a complete mess of it. It's not enough that they
give you back your ten thousand dollars, נושא לו דמי בושתו ודמי
בושת אורחיו. notsei lo dmei boshto v'dmei boshet orchav. They have to
you know they we you can sue for damages for how much
you know you ruined my kid's wedding. It's not enough that they
just give you back your money. Okay now the fact again that
he says מנהג minhag means that you can't really do this under
normal you know like בבא קמא Bava Kamma type of נזיקין nizikin
things right? It's all גרמא בנזיקין, grama b'nizikin, I didn't directly cause
an injury, it wasn't direct בושת, boshet, direct בושת boshet even requires
כוונה kavanah you know intentional. Okay but nevertheless it's a type of
a גרמי garmi it's a type of a תקנה takkanah or קנס
knas that you have to be that we're going to create this
broader liability and the גמרא Gemara assumes that if that's going to
be true in this case it'll be true in I sell you
a product and that leads to you invest all of this money,
I sell you those seeds I'll have to reimburse you.
Where were we? Okay עוד מנהג גדול היה בירושלים Od minhag gadol
haya b'Yerushalayim there was another big practice in Jerusalem
where were we עוד מנהג גדול היה בירושלים od minhag gadol haya
b'Yerushalayim מפה פרוסה על גבי הפתח, mappa prusa al gabi hapetach, if
you put a tablecloth and you sort of you know hung it
on in front of your door, so כל זמן שהמפה פרוסה kol
zman she'mappa prusa as long as people could see the tablecloth hung
by the door אורחין נכנסין orchin nichnasim it was a big call
that you're having your meal and all guests who would like to
come are welcome. Very beautiful. Okay נסתלקה המפה nistalka mappa once it
was removed maybe you had enough guests for the night אין אורחין
נכנסין ein orchin nichnasim they wouldn't come but at least everybody very
visually people are going through town they don't have a place to
eat they see a place with a with a with a big
you know
tablecloth up in the door and they know that they're welcome to
come it's like you know my kids always say I mean I'm
sure we've all said this right right at the סדר seder כל
דכפין ייתי וייכול kol dichfin yeitei v'yeichol very nice to say you're
all settled down the door is closed and you make a big
announcement within the invited guests of כל דכפין ייתי וייכול kol dichfin
yeitei v'yeichol so here was a real way right to make that
announcement. Okay not really related to the previous thing. Anyway so we
see that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel is of
this position that he believes that at least you know there was
a practice to establish a type of a
broad liability and Specifically in the context of this as like professional
liability. I think that's like the common denominator, right? He's not saying
that anytime, oh, anytime I cause some loss to you, right, I
accidentally, I don't know, you know, whatever it was, you were going
to have a, let's say this, you were having your wedding catered,
and the catering truck was coming, and I crashed into the catering
truck, and as a result of it, you didn't get any of
the food and the wedding was, you know, and all and the
meal was a disaster. I don't think he'd say that I'd be
liable, you know, in that case to pay for the embarrassment and
the cost or whatever. I think it's even though the same thing,
you didn't have your whole wedding meal. I think it's specifically a
professional liability. If I'm in the job of being a שוחט shochet
or grinding wheat or selling seed, then I have to have a
heightened responsibility and know that people are relying on me for their,
you know, for their planting to go well, for their wedding to
go well, and I think that's the specific context in which he's
talking.
Yeah, it would seem that there should be a difference based on
the foreseeability of the damage. So for the caterer, it makes sense
to say if the caterer messes up, he should pay for the
whole wedding. Right. But for the butcher who doesn't necessarily know it's
for a wedding and seems pushing it to say he's got to
pay for the whole wedding damages as opposed to.
Aha, you're saying right, aha, aha, that's a good point, like may
like what can the person expect you were going to be using
it for, right, and how much does that factor into the degree
of liability? Right, like I assume most people that come to me,
you're right, are just storing it for their שבת Shabbos meal. It
turns out you were right, you were using this calf for your
wedding. Now you're going to sue me for that reimbursement? Right, that's
an interesting question, I don't know. Yeah, I don't know how he
would figure that. Yeah. Okay, one final thing about this, about this
issue about the level of liability here and the point about when
you're being paid. So I would just need to mention this because
it's a classic debate of תוספות Tosafot and the רמב"ן, Ramban, which
is why by here do we say, you know, based on how
you're being paid, we should figure out an אומדנא umdana is sort
of like a שומר, shomer, and it sounds like your חיוב chiyuv
is either that of a שומר shomer or parallel to that of
a שומר. shomer. That's essentially the idea of this גמרא. Gemara. The
question is, one minute, why aren't you חייב chayav because you're an
אדם המזיק? adam hamazik? You give me your cow, I שחט shachted
it incorrectly. Even if I'm not being paid, okay, then why, and
even if it's an אונס, oness, right, don't we say אדם מועד
לעולם adam muad l'olam that anytime I directly cause damage even if
I have no blame I'm liable? People remember that's a principle in
בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, right? So how come here my liability is
linked to this? I should always be liable even if you don't
pay me, even if it's a complete אונס. oness. So this is
the question the ראשונים Rishonim ask. So תוספות Tosafot uses this and
other סוגיות sugyot to say when we say אדם מועד לעולם, adam
muad l'olam, we don't really mean it. Okay, we really mean even
an אדם המזיק adam hamazik is only liable based on like some
type of a, like only if there's some degree of negligence. Okay,
and because he's only liable with some degree of negligence, that's why
here you really are not going to be responsible if it's a
complete אונס oness and it might matter if you're being paid or
not being paid and so on because an אדם adam is not
really always liable. Okay, so that's תוספות's Tosafot position. The רמב"ן Ramban
says, no, the גמרא Gemara really means it, a person is always
liable as a מזיק mazik even if it wasn't his fault. However,
you know, this is really an interesting question is like that depends
on how we define the relationship of this person to the object.
Like if you're a random person and you trip over your own
two feet or you slip on a puddle that even if it
wasn't your fault or whatever and you slip and you break my,
you know, my vase that was sitting there in רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim or whatever it was, okay, it wasn't your fault, but you
basically are a stranger that destroyed my vase and you're a מזיק.
mazik. That's what we we look up. Okay, you damaged my vase,
מזיק, mazik, מועד לעולם, muad l'olam, you pay the full amount. But
here you're, you have a right to be handling the object. I
asked you to שחט shacht it. I asked you to grind it.
I asked you to bake it. So we don't define you as
a מזיק mazik even though it's true because of a physical thing
you did to my cow, you turned it into a נבילה. neveilah.
But you had a right to be handling my cow and to
be doing something to it. So it's not like you're an outsider
that's, you know, sort of encroaching onto my onto my objects. We
define you as an אומן uman as a craftsperson who is doing
it with license and therefore what we define you as a negligent
אומן uman or a not negligent אומן uman but we don't put
it in the category of אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. Okay, so for
the רמב"ן, Ramban, the reason you're not straight liability is because if
you were a מזיק mazik you would be. But we don't apply
this, we don't look up this in שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch in
הלכות מזיק. Hilchos Mazik. We look at this in שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch in הלכות אומנים Hilchos Umanim and therefore a different set of
rules applies. Okay, whereas for תוספות, Tosafot, you know, no, this is
evidence that a person even an אדם המזיק adam hamazik is not
always liable. Yes.
I don't know if this is different but I thought you were
going to say with the רמב"ן Ramban you put it, you
chose...
That's a different רמב"ן. Ramban. That's a related way he... that's how
he deals with other aspects of תוספות' Tosafos proof. Like תוספות Tosafos
says, like if you're sleeping and I come and I lie down
next to you and you hit me in my sleep or I
put a vessel next to you and you break it in your
sleep, so you're exempt. So תוספות Tosafos says, "Ah, you see? Because
an אדם Adam is not מועד לעולם." muad l'olam. That's why you're
exempt when I put the vessel next to you in your sleep.
And רמב"ן Ramban says, "No, it's because the person who was damaged
is to blame. What are you doing putting your vessel next to
a sleeping person? פשיעת הניזק." pshias hanizak. Okay? This is not negligence
of the ניזק nizak because you're not negligent when you give something
to a responsible party.
Well, there is a certain risk.
That's true. You mean an assumption of risk. Assumption of risk is
different than פשיעת הניזק. pshias hanizak. Maybe it's related. Okay? I always
understood the רמב"ן Ramban understands this is different because your whole category
is different. But you're right, it could be similar to the idea
of assumption of risk. All right, anyway. So interesting things about this
case that came up incidentally. Let's read the next משנה. Mishna. המוכר
פירות לחברו הרי זה מקבל עליו רובע טנופת לסאה. Hamocher peiros l'chavero
harei ze mekabel alav rova tinofes l'sa'ah. So I go ahead, talking
about good examples from פסח, Pesach, the כל דכפין ייתי וייכול. kol
dichfin yeisei v'yeichol. In my box of מצות, matzos, of שמורה מצה,
shmura matzah, okay, there's a little slip in it which is: "This
box contains exactly one pound of matzah. We do our best to
ensure that all the matzos are completely whole. There are a couple
of broken pieces that we throw in to make it the full
pound blah blah blah," right? Anyway, people tell me outside New York,
you buy שמורה מצה shmura matzah and you're lucky if half of
them in a box are still whole. Okay, so here's the question:
I'm selling you wheat and I sell you a pound of wheat,
and you come home and you find that there's a certain amount
of dirt in it, and there's a certain amount of, I don't
know, some type of legumes that got mixed up in the wheat.
Okay, how much could you say, "Hey, this wasn't a pound, this
was only point nine eight of a pound," right? Because there was
some other stuff mixed up. No, you have to assume that there's
going to be every pound of wheat comes with a certain amount
of extraneous material and that's assumed, and it's assumed that you know
that in your מקח mekach to that degree. Okay? המוכר פירות לחברו
הרי זה מקבל עליו
רובע טנופת לסאה. Hamocher peiros l'chavero harei ze mekabel alav rova tinofes
l'sa'ah. A רובע, rova, a quarter of a... of a קב. kav.
There I think six קבין kavin to a סאה. sa'ah. So a
quarter of a קב kav to a סאה sa'ah is going to
be... is going to be ninety... you know, like dirt or whatever
extraneous material to the grain. Okay, so that's one twenty-fourth. It's about...
it's about four percent.
תאנים, Te'einim, if you buy figs,
מקבל עליו עשר מתולעות למאה. mekabel alav eser mesulaos l'me'ah. There can
be ten percent, that's a pretty high level, that are wormy. Okay,
so up to ten percent. Obviously sometimes it'll be one percent, but
up to ten percent you have to understand that that's anticipatable, it
should be anticipated, and you don't have a claim that you now
need me to reimburse you for the wormy ones. מרתף של יין,
Martef shel yayin, of course question is, let's say you found that
eleven were wormy, do I have to now give you one back
or do I have to give you eleven back? I'm serious, it's
a good question, right? Okay. מרתף של יין, Martef shel yayin, you
buy a, you know, a what do you call it? A wine
cellar. מקבל עליו עשר קוססות למאה. mekabel alav eser kosesos l'me'ah. You
have to assume that out of every hundred barrels, up to ten
might be actually slightly spoiled wine. Again, that's a pretty high amount.
Okay, but up
to that should... you know, is something that you have to anticipate
and it's assumed. What? Did you check? Well, yes, I mean, if
you're smart, but you don't want to open the barrel to check
them, right? Because then you let in the air. So what you
might do is you might spot check a few, and so you
spot check the few, and now when you come around to opening
them, I guess it's something like that. Oh, they had a way?
Oh, they had a way to do it without while maintaining the
airtightness of it? Maybe.
It was basically... they had a way to like stick something in...
Right, right, that probably, yeah. So anyway, but for whatever reason you
didn't.
The cases are different, like you could inspect your dates and your
wheat before selling.
No, but the honey you'd have to open up the date to
see if it's wormy, right? Right. And the wheat you would have
to like sift through the whole ten pounds. So right. But I
think that's a good question: if you could have inspected, how does
that change things? Right. Okay. המוכר... okay. קנקנים
בשרון,
if you buy jugs in the Sharon Valley, מקבל עליו עשר פיצצות
למאה. mekabel alav eser pitzetzos l'me'ah. Up to ten of them might
be imperfect and we'll see what that means in the גמרא, Gemara,
why דוקא davka in the שרון. Sharon. Okay, we have one more
minute. תני רב קטינא, Tani Rav Katina, we'll try to do one
more... okay, we'll see one more... get the last line. תני רב
קטינא, Tani Rav Katina, so רב קטינא Katina taught, רובע קטנית לסאה.
rova kitnis l'sa'ah. It's interesting, קטינא and קטנית. kitnis. רובע קטנית Rova
kitnis לסאה. So when we say a רובע rova for a סאה,
sa'ah, four percent, we mean of extraneous stuff that might get mixed
up, like sometimes wild... you know, wild stuff grows amongst the wheat.
So actually there was a great article last פסח Pesach about this
guy who was, you know, had to be like this non-Jewish farmer
that worked with this rabbi to create שמורה מצה shmura matzah and
they had to try to make sure that they didn't have wild
plants growing which were sources of moisture. and as like wild garlic
would sometimes grow up near the wheat and this whole food guy
wrote about it how actually the flour and the wheat it tastes
better because you know because of the type of care that they
make for these other for the purposes of the שמורה מצה. Shmura
Matzah. Anyway, the point being is that the that wild vegetation will
sometimes grow up amongst the wheat. So he's saying this רובע, rova,
this four percent is not about dirt, it's about like legumes and
types of stuff that might have grown up in the wheat and
got mixed up with all the
harvest, okay? רובע קטנית ופרורית לא, va-fruris lo, but any dirt you're
not responsible, you know, you should not have to expect and you
could be reimbursed for the weight of any dirt that you got.
Talmud says one minute, ואמר רבה בר חייא va-amar Rabbah bar Chiya
כתש כתיסבא katus katisva משמיה דרבה mishmei d'Rabba בורר צרור מגרנו שח
borer tzeror migarno she-cha anyway, you know, let's stop there. Okay, so
the claim is that you're not liable for that that the wheat
could be clean of any dirt and the only thing that's presumed
that you have to assume that could be there is mixed up
is some like other types of like you know legumes or whatever
and we'll see about this tomorrow about whether that actually is what
the משנה mishna means or not.